export const questions = [

  // data structure easy 
  {
    id: 1,
    subject: "Data Structures",
    topic: "Arrays",
    difficulty: "easy",
    question: "What is the first index of an array?",
    options: ["0", "1", "-1", "Depends on language"],
    answer: "0",
  },
  {
    id: 2,
    subject: "Data Structures",
    topic: "Queue",
    difficulty: "easy",
    question: "Which data structure follows FIFO principle?",
    options: ["Stack", "Queue", "Tree", "Graph"],
    answer: "Queue",
  },
  {
    id: 3,
    subject: "Data Structures",
    topic: "Stack",
    difficulty: "easy",
    question: "Which operation removes the top element from a stack?",
    options: ["push()", "enqueue()", "pop()", "insert()"],
    answer: "pop()",
  },
  {
    id: 4,
    subject: "Data Structures",
    topic: "Linked List",
    difficulty: "easy",
    question: "Each node in a singly linked list contains:",
    options: [
      "Data and next pointer",
      "Only data",
      "Two pointers",
      "Only pointer"
    ],
    answer: "Data and next pointer",
  },
  {
    id: 5,
    subject: "Data Structures",
    topic: "Arrays",
    difficulty: "easy",
    question: "Accessing an element in an array takes:",
    options: ["O(1)", "O(n)", "O(log n)", "O(n²)"],
    answer: "O(1)",
  },

  // data structure medium
  {
    id: 6,
    subject: "Data Structures",
    topic: "Searching",
    difficulty: "medium",
    question: "Binary search requires the array to be:",
    options: ["Unsorted", "Sorted", "Reversed", "Circular"],
    answer: "Sorted",
  },
  {
    id: 7,
    subject: "Data Structures",
    topic: "Recursion",
    difficulty: "medium",
    question: "Recursion uses which data structure internally?",
    options: ["Queue", "Stack", "Tree", "Graph"],
    answer: "Stack",
  },
  {
    id: 8,
    subject: "Data Structures",
    topic: "Linked List",
    difficulty: "medium",
    question: "Insertion at the beginning of a linked list takes:",
    options: ["O(1)", "O(n)", "O(log n)", "O(n²)"],
    answer: "O(1)",
  },
  {
    id: 9,
    subject: "Data Structures",
    topic: "Sorting",
    difficulty: "medium",
    question: "Which sorting algorithm has average time complexity O(n log n)?",
    options: ["Bubble Sort", "Selection Sort", "Merge Sort", "Insertion Sort"],
    answer: "Merge Sort",
  },
  {
    id: 10,
    subject: "Data Structures",
    topic: "Queue",
    difficulty: "medium",
    question: "Circular queue is used to:",
    options: [
      "Avoid memory wastage",
      "Sort elements",
      "Reverse elements",
      "Delete nodes"
    ],
    answer: "Avoid memory wastage",
  },

  //data structure hard
  {
    id: 11,
    subject: "Data Structures",
    topic: "Searching",
    difficulty: "hard",
    question: "Time complexity of binary search is:",
    options: ["O(n)", "O(log n)", "O(n log n)", "O(1)"],
    answer: "O(log n)",
  },
  {
    id: 12,
    subject: "Data Structures",
    topic: "Sorting",
    difficulty: "hard",
    question: "Worst-case time complexity of Quick Sort is:",
    options: ["O(n)", "O(n log n)", "O(n²)", "O(log n)"],
    answer: "O(n²)",
  },
  {
    id: 13,
    subject: "Data Structures",
    topic: "Tree",
    difficulty: "hard",
    question: "Maximum number of nodes in a binary tree of height h is:",
    options: ["2^h - 1", "2h", "h²", "h log h"],
    answer: "2^h - 1",
  },
  {
    id: 14,
    subject: "Data Structures",
    topic: "Graph",
    difficulty: "hard",
    question: "DFS traversal uses which data structure?",
    options: ["Queue", "Stack", "Heap", "Array"],
    answer: "Stack",
  },
  {
    id: 15,
    subject: "Data Structures",
    topic: "Hashing",
    difficulty: "hard",
    question: "Collision in hashing occurs when:",
    options: [
      "Two keys map to same index",
      "Array is sorted",
      "Index is empty",
      "Table is full"
    ],
    answer: "Two keys map to same index",
  },

  //operating system easy
{
  id: 16,
  subject: "Operating Systems",
  topic: "Basics",
  difficulty: "easy",
  question: "Which of the following is an operating system?",
  options: ["Windows", "Python", "HTML", "Java"],
  answer: "Windows",
},
{
  id: 17,
  subject: "Operating Systems",
  topic: "Process",
  difficulty: "easy",
  question: "A program in execution is called:",
  options: ["Thread", "Process", "Compiler", "Scheduler"],
  answer: "Process",
},
{
  id: 18,
  subject: "Operating Systems",
  topic: "Memory",
  difficulty: "easy",
  question: "Which memory is fastest?",
  options: ["RAM", "Cache", "Hard Disk", "ROM"],
  answer: "Cache",
},
{
  id: 19,
  subject: "Operating Systems",
  topic: "CPU Scheduling",
  difficulty: "easy",
  question: "FCFS stands for:",
  options: ["First Come First Serve", "Fast CPU First System", "First CPU First Serve", "None"],
  answer: "First Come First Serve",
},
{
  id: 20,
  subject: "Operating Systems",
  topic: "Deadlock",
  difficulty: "easy",
  question: "Deadlock occurs when:",
  options: [
    "Processes wait indefinitely",
    "CPU is free",
    "Memory is empty",
    "System shuts down"
  ],
  answer: "Processes wait indefinitely",
},

// operating system medium
{
  id: 21,
  subject: "Operating Systems",
  topic: "CPU Scheduling",
  difficulty: "medium",
  question: "Which scheduling algorithm may cause starvation?",
  options: ["FCFS", "Round Robin", "Priority Scheduling", "FIFO"],
  answer: "Priority Scheduling",
},
{
  id: 22,
  subject: "Operating Systems",
  topic: "Memory",
  difficulty: "medium",
  question: "Paging helps to:",
  options: [
    "Eliminate external fragmentation",
    "Increase CPU speed",
    "Reduce threads",
    "Increase disk space"
  ],
  answer: "Eliminate external fragmentation",
},
{
  id: 23,
  subject: "Operating Systems",
  topic: "Deadlock",
  difficulty: "medium",
  question: "Which is NOT a condition for deadlock?",
  options: [
    "Mutual Exclusion",
    "Hold and Wait",
    "Preemption",
    "Circular Wait"
  ],
  answer: "Preemption",
},
{
  id: 24,
  subject: "Operating Systems",
  topic: "Process",
  difficulty: "medium",
  question: "Context switching occurs when:",
  options: [
    "CPU switches between processes",
    "Memory is full",
    "Disk fails",
    "User logs out"
  ],
  answer: "CPU switches between processes",
},

{
  id: 25,
  subject: "Operating Systems",
  topic: "Threads",
  difficulty: "medium",
  question: "Threads within same process share:",
  options: ["Code section", "Registers", "Stack", "Separate memory"],
  answer: "Code section",
},

//operating system hard
{
  id: 26,
  subject: "Operating Systems",
  topic: "Scheduling",
  difficulty: "hard",
  question: "Round Robin scheduling depends on:",
  options: [
    "Time quantum",
    "Memory size",
    "CPU speed",
    "Number of threads"
  ],
  answer: "Time quantum",
},
{
  id: 27,
  subject: "Operating Systems",
  topic: "Memory",
  difficulty: "hard",
  question: "Thrashing occurs when:",
  options: [
    "Excessive paging",
    "CPU overheating",
    "Disk failure",
    "Cache overflow"
  ],
  answer: "Excessive paging",
},
{
  id: 28,
  subject: "Operating Systems",
  topic: "Deadlock",
  difficulty: "hard",
  question: "Banker’s algorithm is used for:",
  options: [
    "Deadlock avoidance",
    "CPU scheduling",
    "Memory allocation",
    "File management"
  ],
  answer: "Deadlock avoidance",
},
{
  id: 29,
  subject: "Operating Systems",
  topic: "Memory",
  difficulty: "hard",
  question: "Which replacement algorithm may suffer from Belady’s anomaly?",
  options: ["FIFO", "LRU", "Optimal", "Clock"],
  answer: "FIFO",
},
{
  id: 30,
  subject: "Operating Systems",
  topic: "Process",
  difficulty: "hard",
  question: "Zombie process is:",
  options: [
    "Terminated but not removed from process table",
    "Running process",
    "Sleeping process",
    "Deadlocked process"
  ],
  answer: "Terminated but not removed from process table",
},
//computer network easy
{
  id: 31,
  subject: "Computer Networks",
  topic: "Basics",
  difficulty: "easy",
  question: "What does LAN stand for?",
  options: [
    "Local Area Network",
    "Large Area Network",
    "Low Access Network",
    "Linear Area Network"
  ],
  answer: "Local Area Network",
},
{
  id: 32,
  subject: "Computer Networks",
  topic: "Protocols",
  difficulty: "easy",
  question: "Which protocol is used to browse websites?",
  options: ["HTTP", "FTP", "SMTP", "ARP"],
  answer: "HTTP",
},
{
  id: 33,
  subject: "Computer Networks",
  topic: "IP",
  difficulty: "easy",
  question: "IPv4 address consists of:",
  options: ["32 bits", "64 bits", "16 bits", "128 bits"],
  answer: "32 bits",
},
{
  id: 34,
  subject: "Computer Networks",
  topic: "OSI Model",
  difficulty: "easy",
  question: "How many layers are in OSI model?",
  options: ["5", "6", "7", "8"],
  answer: "7",
},
{
  id: 35,
  subject: "Computer Networks",
  topic: "Transmission",
  difficulty: "easy",
  question: "Which device connects two networks?",
  options: ["Router", "Switch", "Hub", "Repeater"],
  answer: "Router",
},
//computer network medium
{
  id: 36,
  subject: "Computer Networks",
  topic: "Protocols",
  difficulty: "medium",
  question: "Which protocol is used for secure web browsing?",
  options: ["HTTP", "HTTPS", "FTP", "ARP"],
  answer: "HTTPS",
},
{
  id: 37,
  subject: "Computer Networks",
  topic: "OSI Model",
  difficulty: "medium",
  question: "Which OSI layer handles encryption?",
  options: [
    "Application",
    "Presentation",
    "Transport",
    "Network"
  ],
  answer: "Presentation",
},
{
  id: 38,
  subject: "Computer Networks",
  topic: "IP",
  difficulty: "medium",
  question: "IPv6 address length is:",
  options: ["32 bits", "64 bits", "128 bits", "256 bits"],
  answer: "128 bits",
},
{
  id: 39,
  subject: "Computer Networks",
  topic: "Transport",
  difficulty: "medium",
  question: "Which protocol is connection-oriented?",
  options: ["UDP", "TCP", "ICMP", "ARP"],
  answer: "TCP",
},
{
  id: 40,
  subject: "Computer Networks",
  topic: "Switching",
  difficulty: "medium",
  question: "Which switching technique is used in internet?",
  options: [
    "Circuit Switching",
    "Packet Switching",
    "Message Switching",
    "Hybrid Switching"
  ],
  answer: "Packet Switching",
},
//computer network hard
{
  id: 41,
  subject: "Computer Networks",
  topic: "Routing",
  difficulty: "hard",
  question: "Which algorithm is used in link-state routing?",
  options: [
    "Dijkstra’s Algorithm",
    "Bellman-Ford",
    "Prim’s Algorithm",
    "Kruskal’s Algorithm"
  ],
  answer: "Dijkstra’s Algorithm",
},
{
  id: 42,
  subject: "Computer Networks",
  topic: "Transport",
  difficulty: "hard",
  question: "TCP congestion control uses:",
  options: [
    "Slow Start",
    "Fast Retransmit",
    "Congestion Avoidance",
    "All of the above"
  ],
  answer: "All of the above",
},
{
  id: 43,
  subject: "Computer Networks",
  topic: "Security",
  difficulty: "hard",
  question: "SSL operates at which OSI layer?",
  options: [
    "Transport",
    "Application",
    "Presentation",
    "Network"
  ],
  answer: "Presentation",
},
{
  id: 44,
  subject: "Computer Networks",
  topic: "IP",
  difficulty: "hard",
  question: "Subnet mask is used to:",
  options: [
    "Identify network and host portion",
    "Encrypt data",
    "Increase bandwidth",
    "Route packets"
  ],
  answer: "Identify network and host portion",
},
{
  id: 45,
  subject: "Computer Networks",
  topic: "DNS",
  difficulty: "hard",
  question: "DNS primarily uses which protocol?",
  options: ["TCP", "UDP", "HTTP", "FTP"],
  answer: "UDP",
},


];